this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software hello this is Stephan tilaka
for software engineering radio my guest
today is Adrian Cockcroft Adrian is
probably best known for leading
Netflix's efforts to move to a fully
cloud-based highly dynamic architecture
he also worked as a distinguished
engineer at Sun Microsystems and
co-founded eBay's research labs today
Adrian works as a technology advisor for
battery ventures Adrian welcome to the
show
as usual I would like to ask you to
start us off by introducing yourself who
are you and what do you do hi there
thanks for having me on this show so I'm
a technologist and software developer
been around for a long time it's sort of
just start from the beginning I a
startup with a physics degree based out
of the UK and worked for about I think
about five years as a software engineer
that's my job title so that seems to
tightline up with the with the podcast
building embedded real-time systems and
kind of all kinds of different kinds of
software but the company core Cambridge
consultants in the UK we are one of the
first users of Sun workstations as our
development platform back in the mid 80s
and eventually sun opened an office
nearby and I joined them so then spent
about five years as a systems engineer
that Sun in the UK and then moved to the
US about 20 years ago and worked through
different parts of engineering at Sun
basically concentrating on performance
and capacity planning towards the end
Sun I was a distinguished engineer
basically around that performance
capacity planning topic or at a book
called some performance and tuning that
a lot of people have which has a
nice picture of a red Porsche on the
front which most people remember it by
they've cover rather than the title and
the last job I had at Sun was the chief
architect for high-performance computing
and in 2004 son did one of its shrinking
laying people off phases and that whole
group got laid off so then I joined eBay
I'd worked with eBay a bit on and off
over the years helping them scale so I
worked there as a basically a sort of
distinguished availability architect or
something I think was the titles working
on scaling and availability I learned a
lot about large scale systems and
customer-facing systems rather than
enterprise you know selling to
enterprises I've helped form the eBay
research labs there's some interesting
work there then in 2007 I joined Netflix
and I think Netflix is on the verge of
launching in Germany and France in the
next sometimes in the next month -
that'd be interesting to to see how that
rolls out but I joined Netflix and
managed a team of software developers
for about three or four years that
towards the end of that period we
decided to move to the cloud and I led
the team or one of the teams that moved
to the part of the platform to the cloud
we then formed a platform team within
the company and I became the the
architect for that team in started going
out doing talks outside Netflix
explaining to people this is how we did
cloud this is what we're doing and you
know the reaction to that started off as
incomprehension worked its way through
denial - okay this looks useful and
finally at the end of last year there
was getting quite a lot of interest
outside Netflix and I moved to work for
a venture capital company called Battery
Ventures and that's been my last know
what seven months or so where I'm doing
a similar kind of thing spending a lot
of time at conferences explaining you
know talking about new technology and
I'm spending a lot of time with the
portfolio companies that batteries
invested in helping them scale become
more available moved to cloud
and just generally you know have to see
if I can get them to be more valuable
more quickly that's what the feces care
about okay so it's it's really hard to
it's it's hard to read an article or to
read any sort of article these days that
doesn't somehow mention the cloud or
cloud computing
despite that how would you define those
those things what is what is the cloud
and what does cloud computing actually
mean to you I think the biggest change
if if you're if you're working in a
company and you think you know I need
some machines to do something and you
have to file a ticket and wait to
somebody else to get around to sorting
out that ticket and some big companies
that takes a month two months to get
just a single machine the real thing
about cloud computing is it's
self-service you make a API call and
bunch of machines turn up a few minutes
later that's the most fundamental
difference it speeds up the whole
procurement cycle and it means that you
can give machines back because you can
get the back again in a few minutes so
it makes everything much more dynamic
you can use the cloud as a just a faster
way to do the things you used to do in
data centers but they're really
interesting things come when you start
realizing what happens when you use it
in a much more dynamic way and machines
become ephemeral you can turn them on
turn them off and use a machine for a
couple of hours give it back that's
really the essence of cloud I think it
really comes down to the ability
self-service tools in the hands of the
developers to go do things themselves
rather than making what operations used
to do into an API I don't really care
whether it's public cloud like AWS or a
private cloud inside the company as long
as it sort of should be on demand and
there should be enough capacity there
that whatever you need to do it's just
there yeah
so that would limit the private
applicability to companies that can
afford to offer so many machines
physically that it makes this possible
for almost any kind of thing that
developers could think of I don't think
it limits I mean if you ask for a
thousand machines and you don't have a
thousand machines you're still going to
have a problem and it's possible to run
out on AWS right one of the advantages
of public cloud is that it is you're
sharing your polling a much larger
piece of capacity so think of it as
being a small fish in a big pond and it
really works well when you are a small
fish in a big pond if you the
alternative I have a diagram somewhere
there's a shark in a paddling pool the
Sharks don't fit simpad fit in paddling
pools if you end up being a really big
user in a really small cloud doesn't
matter whether it's public or private
it's just not going to work so well so
just think of it as the statistical
averaging of lots of different use cases
into a big pool of resources makes it
look as if it's sort of effectively
limitless but that only applies up to
some you know some kind of scale so how
did how did Netflix end up moving to the
cloud was the history behind that the
history is that Netflix started off as a
DVD shipping company it wasn't even seen
as a very big technology company at the
time when I joined they were well known
for personalization algorithms as their
main sort of interesting technology
rather than scale or anything like that
and they had around six million
customers when I joined in No 7 and
those customers typically every weekend
they would pull up the website decide
what DVDs they wanted to have shipped in
the next and what order by shuffling
their queue and then every time they
sent a disc back we'd send him a down
another one so the interaction with
Netflix was sending a disk in through
the postal service that required a few
tens of web servers and a few of
back-end machines and a big database it
was very severe monolithic centralized
app so that was that was o 7 and in O 7
we launched streaming with a very small
catalogue but it started to take off
quite quickly
now when you interact with the streaming
service every click it has to go to the
website every time you decide you want
to watch something you browse around the
web site you click Play then there's a
lot of traffic that goes back and forth
figuring out what to do figuring out
finding the machine so finding the the
movie doing a giving you a security key
to decode that movie and then logging
your the activity so that we can make
sure that there's good quality of
service you know
there any rebuff is what speedy running
out which CDN you're talking to there's
an enormous number of transactions to
the back end is maybe a thousand times
higher than a DVD service it's it's some
large number of orders of magnitude more
traffic which was fine when we were just
starting out with just a small number of
machines so at a small number of movies
and not many customers using it but the
usage rate started to increase very
rapidly because there's nothing stopping
you from watching lots of movies you
didn't have to send the DVD back and
wait for another one so we started
getting a lot of people doing sort of
binge watching of content so the number
of interactions people had with Netflix
the number of things they watched went
up and the number of interactions with
the website per view went up by a huge
amount so that basically meant that we
looked at our data center and this small
couple of machines in the corner that
were put into initially launched
streaming we're just running out of
capacity incredibly quickly and in 2008
there was a big outage that Netflix had
were or the the central monolithic app
broke and it was actually the storage
problem divided corruption in the san
corrupted Oracle and it was a big mess
and as a result of that we basically
decided we weren't very good at running
stuff in the data center and they
started looking out for how are we gonna
scale this incredible future workload
where we didn't know how fast it was
going to grow and that really comes down
to the core of why this is interesting
was didn't know we couldn't predict how
much capacity were gonna need and in
2010 or 2009 removed some of the backend
batch workloads like in encoding movies
to the work to the cloud and in 2010
moved the front-end website to the cloud
in 2011 moved the database backends of
the master copies of all the data are in
the cloud and in 2012 they did open
sourcing the the tooling we'd built to
do that I guess that's probably the main
history points so I just I'm just
assuming that he would you would
probably agree there was the right
decision for for Netflix to do this in
hindsight at you would you recommend it
to to others as
swell how dependent is it on being in
that kind of business that can
essentially grow in them totally
unforeseeable way how dynamic do you
have to be to be able to make sense of
that or that move
well it's certainly more fun to be
working at companies that are growing
fast
rightfully what your shares need to go
up so if you've got a very static
workload or slowly shrinking workload
it's but you know and your app isn't
changing very fast it's probably best to
just leave it alone then and the DVD
business is still running on the
monolithic platform on the you know big
old IBM PC Riis machine on Oracle and
it's I don't think they've changed the
code in that for the last few years but
it still has that it still now has six
million users the DVD business I think
peaked at about 12 million and then went
back down to six Netflix now is 50
million users on streaming so you know
that was the that's what drove it was
this this growth so you can optimize if
you have very predictable workloads but
you know predictable workloads are
somewhat boring places to work out so
yeah so there's this kind of there's two
kinds of ways you can think about a
business if you're if you're if you
become a commodity and a utility really
then you want to optimize the cost and
you're just looking for efficiency and
cost and predictability and there's a
lot of technologies you can apply to
that but then a lot of businesses now
the world is moving so fast that what
really matters is how fast you can
develop something new and as soon as you
get to that becoming the thing that
drives your company as soon as you get
to the speed of development and that
everything is driven by software now
everything internet of things is
touching everybody so if everything is
software based and software it takes the
longest part of developing anything
speeding up software development is a
kit key thing it's like a universal good
for all businesses now and what I'm
seeing is cloud is part of speeding up
it's not the whole thing but it's part
of speeding up software development and
that's there is a general thing that
everybody is figuring out how to
so let's let's try or I will try to not
turn this into a into a business podcast
though that would be interesting but
still I want to ask if you though if you
look at those three things like the
growth driving down cost and speeding
things up then it seems that your
opinion is that it's that the cloud
optimizes for growth and speed and not
so much for cost is that it there are a
lot of companies that have very
overburdened
bloated costs in their infrastructure
they have like an incredibly complicated
San storage system with very high cost
vendors in it if that's your environment
then going to a public cloud is usually
lower cost because it's built it's a
it's a switch to a commodity framework
commodity Hardware you can buy by the
hour you don't have to pay a lot upfront
and you get a lot more software
constructs and a lot more open source
constructs in there so if you're making
that transition as part of the cloud
transition then it's also usually a cost
reduction if you look at well I could
build this you know low cost commodity
hardware with open source software on it
and stick that in a data center
somewhere then the costs end up being
dependent kind of what you're doing and
how you're doing it and how much
capacity you need to buy when but yeah
certainly possible to build things that
are cheaper than the cloud but you have
to build it at the same way that the
cloud is built and a lot of enterprises
just aren't built that way they're their
intrinsic costs are if you take the
number of machines they have in their
total IT budget and divide the two you
find that they're paying in many dollars
per hour for a machine that they could
get for a few cents in the cloud
mm-hm so one of the things that your
internet was that things are changing
from an architectural perspective from a
software architecture perspective as
well if you move to the cloud that you
maybe end up building things differently
what are some of the things that you
think are different once you decide to
move to such a cloud-based
infrastructure you can use cloud as just
a faster way to do data center stuff and
that misses most of the benefit I think
the real benefit comes when you start
doing things that you could not have
done in your data center you can treat
do hardware experiments that last a few
days on a huge scale scattered all over
the world something that you just you
wouldn't even go to your Ops guys and
say hey I need a globally distributed
database with a hundred notes in it and
a couple hundred terabytes of
solid-state disk and I'd like it this
afternoon and six different rioters and
whether we did this we did this without
asking permission it took about 20
minutes to create when we're at Netflix
we were trying to run an experiment to
build a very write intensive globally
distributed database to see what would
happen it was the decision to do it was
while we were walking out of a meeting
the guy I was talking to wandered by
somebody else's cuba's than to set it up
that afternoon it was created we put 18
terabytes of data we pulled from our
backups into it pushed it across the
world and then yeah hammered hammered
the thing as hard as we could with all
kinds of error in failure injection to
make sure it worked well in two or three
days later we removed it yeah that was
yeah 96 machines each machine was 64 gig
of ram and 2 terabytes of SSD if you
can't do that if you have real
infrastructure because it takes too long
to get approval that's a multi-million
dollar machine I don't even know what it
would cost but it was a know a few
hundred dollars an hour was what it
actually costs and for the value we got
out of it then we went to a meeting the
following week and said ok we just
proved this works and when you go to a
meeting with working code or or
benchmarks near examples you win
arguments and this was there was an
argument going on about how we were
going to do distributed systems and
whether we could rely on hi we have what
kind of bandwidth we could get in a
global cloud and we were running about
nine gigabits of bandwidth in in parts
of this thing so it basically just
closed down this whole argument and said
well this works we proved it and
therefore went okay I guess we can use
that and and it short-circuited any
enormous amount of what would have been
debate and justification and all of the
things you'd be doing and arguing with
people about how much it would cost and
all that kind of stuff
so that's that's actually the idea of
doing experiments being able to try
stuff out we are retiring risk do you
say you're taking things that might not
work and checking out and see if they
work with and there are lots of cases
where where that's been a very powerful
technique mm-hmm
does it affect the the actual running
production software as well that did you
build it differently because it was
running on the cloud or differently from
how you would have build it if it were
if it had been reading your own
datacenter
yes it's built to be dynamic and and I
you want to talk about sort of simian
army things this is really where it ties
in there's market actual principles
which people kind of have heard of the
chaos monkey what that really is is it
it's enforcing an architectural
principle the principle it's quite how
can you explain what the chaos monkey is
because I'm not sure everybody may
explain the principle and then of the
obvious why it makes sense so there's a
there's an analogy going around right
now which is about capital versus pets
and you see in a few talks on this
subject where if there's machines in
production that you know their name and
if they go down everyone gets upset
that's a pet that's a pet machine it's
like your pet cat right you have to take
it to the vet if it gets it the other
kinds of machines are cattle it's a herd
of cattle in a field you're getting so
many gallons of milk and if a few of
them die
you get a slightly less milk that day
you buy some more cattle right the
principle the Netflix adopted was that
everything in production is a is a herd
of cattle everything is an auto scaler
there are no pets there are no
individual machines that if
individuality would care about so once
you've established that principle you
have to test that principle by going
around killing individual machines at
random which is what the cows monkey
does it just picks between 9:00 and 5:00
during the week it will just go around
stopping machines say I'm sorry this cow
is dead and the system within the auto
scale you would then just automatically
replace it and if somebody snuck a
individual machine into production and
the chaos monkey killed it and they got
upset who say we shouldn't have done
that
right so it's in for the architectural
principle by having a process there
which is sort of forcing the developers
to think in this new way to everything
you know it is an order scale curve even
if there's only one machine in the group
it's got to be a stateless disposable
machine that can be restarted and they
took it to an it to the next level with
the data layer is a triple replicated
Cassandra back-end and they actually
killed those off as well including the
disks that are inside the instances so
you might lose a few hundred gigabytes
of data when you delete the instance
it's not an attached storage model it's
an it's a the disks are inside the
instances but that it's replaced and
then the data is resynchronize from the
other two copies and just keep going so
they're proving that you can build a
ephemeral data layer as well so that's
really the that's a different way of
thinking from a sort of data center
mentality where you'd say these machines
should always stay up and they can make
perfect machines instead of that you're
creating fleets of machines or herds of
machines which are extremely resilient
because you can you can lose large
numbers of them and everything still
works what did she use to to to
dynamically reconnect stuff I would
imagine that there's something that
needs to be registered in the load
balancer there are some machines depend
on each other whether virtualized or not
to know who to talk to or who who is
part of the group they're supposed to
talk to how did you handle that did you
have to build that yourself or were
you're able to use stuff available on
the platform there's two two answers to
that so at the edge the the things that
are externally visible there's a DNS
name for a thing right you're gonna go
hit an API at a well-known symbol so the
DNS basically takes a name and spreads
it across usually three zones in AWS
some that we use the the Amazon or these
these arms and a elastic load balancer
they'll be the first level of the elbe
is a DNS blitter that basically just
round robins the requests across the
three zones then the next layer is as
a set of machines that run something
that's logically equivalent to something
like a cheap Roxy and it's you register
back-end machines with that it health
checks them and maintains a pool of
services service machines behind the the
load balancer behind a large tier of
proxy servers so that's the edge and you
register into the you basically you take
an order scale group and you register it
with a load balancer and it if the AWS
handles you know all of the machines
coming in and out it that's the edge but
when you get inside the system you want
to be able to talk between machines and
you can either do it using like a
message bus or something like that but
what Netflix uses is a service registry
that with a lot of metadata in it which
is called Eureka it's one of the
open-source projects and this basically
just a Java Tomcat server that was
dedicated for this use everybody calls
it every 30 seconds says I'm here this
is more information about me and then
they another call around or about every
30 seconds says tell me where everybody
is you got a map of the world back from
it that tells you all of the instances
and what their names are and metadata
about them so then when you want to call
a service by name you look it up in this
map and basically say I need a service
ABC okay there's ABC I don't care what
version I'm calling but here's the
latest version of ABC that's taking
traffic it's a there's an instance I'll
go call that one and you basically it'll
call once they're in the same zone and
things like that so that's some code
that was wrapped around the jersey
library sort of HTTP client java code
that was embedded into the client-side
code for the platform which is a open
sourced as a project or driven by
netflix unger hub so ribbon is the
client-side code in the middle server
side component which is a base server
that's called carry on with a que and
those two carry on and ribbon basically
work with eureka to find each other and
make all of the direct calls in a very
highly available very flexible way
with a lot of options and how you can
route traffic okay so I would love to
spend about six hours talking about just
all of those libraries but in moving to
somewhat of a meta level how do you how
did you figure out to sort how to solve
the bootstrap problems how does Eureka
itself stay up and available and
replicated because it can't use Eureka
because it is Eureka right how do you
standalone services that just sit there
so you were the typical arrangement that
the web the way you roll this out is you
take an AWS region and you roll and you
pick three zones within that region
because you want to triple replicate
everything so then what you do is you
start with one copy of Eureka in each
zone and they they are they actually
talk to route 53 the DNS service and
create a DNS they register themselves in
DNS so there is a one well known DNS
rendezvous point that everyone goes to
and that is spread across these three so
you can go to any of the three but it
all sort of prefer to go to your local
one and then they talk to site they have
a sideways protocol so they replicate
side to side so the three copies but the
system is actually very robust it if
you're familiar with the cap theorem
most most coordination services are try
to be too consistent in my opinion and
that when you partition the system you
they fail in nasty ways and you can you
know you can't get a consistent view so
they stopped working
Yuriko is an AP system it it's available
when partition defect the system still
works even if you kill all of those
nodes and that was something that was
developed over a while because
occasionally things fail so basically
you can kill all of the name services
and the system look everything still
works it just freezes you can't create
new machines in the service but
everything still runs and when Eureka
restarts it loads up all its state and
rediscovers everything and you can do
that you know it's it's a it's basically
built to be extremely highly available
in robust rather than to be as
consistent in the same way that
something like uzuki
would be we looked at basing it on
zookeeper but zookeeper has these
failure modes which actually make it
less desirable can you talk about sixty
seconds about the cap theorem on out how
which parts of it do you apply or which
side you lean to or link to at Netflix
and Journal is AP door you have to
explain what it is and is AP the general
yeah way you build things there yeah I
mean you have to decide at some point
where the consistency or availability is
most important to you and the problem
you know as a physics physicist yeah
everything is actually inconsistent
because you know because of Einstein and
relativity and whatever if you go deep
into the bowels of the with the
algorithms but the the basic principle
with Netflix is that no partition or
failure should take out the service so
it will be definitely lean very heavily
on the availability side when things are
partitioned which means if you slice
Netflix up and drop all the networks
between all the different parts of the
system it actually continues to work in
its in the isolated systems will just
carry on working and they will gradually
drift and become inconsistent with the
rest of the system when you reconnect it
there's the last right wins basically
takes over usually Cassandra kicks in
and whoever wrote the piece of data last
ends up overwriting whatever was written
in the meantime so you it gradually gets
back to being a consistent system
although you may lose a few updates if
you modified something and there's
something in it and then it got modified
somewhere else it generally it doesn't
it's better to deal with the
inconsistency issues than to be down
that's really that and for a service
like Netflix where with 50 million
people trying to watch movies around the
world they have an expectation when they
turn on a TV set that it should just
work you know they shouldn't be little
messages saying sorry we're down right
now people you know it's hard to tell a
three-year-old that they can't watch
their yeah dinosaur cartoons because
Netflix is very bothered right so yeah I
think it's it's this is obviously very
convincing for this particular use case
was it something that you applied in the
same way when
accounting was was restor when it was
you know of billing and then all of
those whose cases with people people
typically expect stuff to be 100%
consistent because they're very so used
to that already to universally apply the
principle is applied to the customer
facing things that could cause an outage
in the service so many if you hit the
play button you should get a movie
playing anything that's in the loop for
doing that needs to be highly available
the stuff in the backend that doesn't
need to be highly available like billing
systems need to be more consistent but
they aren't in that play loop right for
Netflix in particular the signup process
you don't want to drop a customer during
the signup process but if you saw some
reason can't you know validate their
credit card right now you can kind of
say well I'll just let you get the
service and will validate that credit
card
you know asynchronously but most of the
time you want to do their fraud analysis
and things synchronously so it's there's
a few things where you want to be
consistent but they generally are
relatively low traffic things that don't
affect the service delivery itself so
you partition those things off into a
separate space there's this use of
things like zookeeper give you the
ability to do sort of globally
consistent sort of locking and things
that look a bit more like transactions
and things which way where you can
enforce consistency and yeah leader
election whatever but generally you want
to avoid that in things that that the
customer facing part of the service and
that that distinction if that
distinction is kept fairly clean at
Netflix mm-hm makes perfect sense um so
one of the things that you mentioned the
beginning of the show is that the
original application handling the DVD
sending our business was a monolith and
one thing one topic that I know you're
interested in is splitting up more or
less into smaller units these days
typically called microservices did you
apply that principle at Netflix and if
so how did it turn out there it just we
didn't call it micro services at the
time but what we found was that Netflix
at that time had a roughly a hundred
developers bill
the monolith and we were stomping on
each other's code all the time
this is a very common problem there's
two problems with the monolith which as
you scale that become a become big
issues when you're when there's two or
three guys writing some code yeah it
doesn't matter so you people generally
start off building a single monolithic
application because that's the fastest
way you can get something done and then
at some point your organization scales
and you want to and a few other
different attributes kick in so I wonder
this isn't bad it's just that they are
hard to scale in large organizations so
then just be clear on that
so the way the problem we had was to two
problems one was that everyone was
trying to modify the movie object and
everyone was trying to modify the
customer object and just about every
code change that they made and so the
when you developed your code you wrote a
bunch of jar files and then QA would
pick up these jar files and try and
integrate them all into all the branches
into a into a you know the next version
of the code that you were going to roll
out and they just have all kinds of
collisions and problems and it be back
and forth so it took longer and longer
to get the code delivered because the
integration phase got harder and harder
and the QA guys became a bigger
bottleneck because everyone was breaking
each other's code so that was one
problem the fix for that is to separate
out the code and be couple the teams so
that each individual engineer instead of
developing a a jar file that depended
upon everyone else's jar files in a very
intimate way was developing a service
that had very clear connections over
rest calls or whatever had a very clear
set of interfaces to everyone else's
code and so that meant that the tangling
together of all of the objects couldn't
really happen because they were all in
different address spaces and how many of
those things did you end up building it
at Netflix just robbed it not looking
for an exact number just is it it
doesn't say it's showing so well it's
just to go back to the the other reason
that monitors are a problem is if you're
trying to roll a weekly or bi-weekly
update that's monolithic you know that
Netflix was on a two-week train release
mode
and something broken you have to roll
back the 99 other things that would that
release also got rolled back because
they were part of that release right so
one broken thing blocks everything out
so that's the other problem at the
operational delivery point rather than
the QA this is sort of rather than the
QA team blocking this is what happens at
the ops level right so breaking into
things into separate pieces that can
deploy independently breaks that problem
because now it you know you're not
blocked by somebody else's bug so
everything becomes much more fluid so
what happens is you get you know a few
hundred engineers and they individually
are building their own service and so
fairly rapidly you have a few hundred
services and Netflix now has maybe you
know five hundred to a thousand services
and then there are multiple versions of
those services running as well because
you don't shut down the old version of
something when you start the new one
because now you've already got this
layer this metadata layer in Eureka
handles the routing of traffic between
things and it can knows about versions
so if you have a service that depends on
version 3 of some other service version
3 at that service will just always be
there even if a version 4 comes along in
version 5 comes along and somebody else
wants a new feature of that service so
they're using version 5 but it doesn't
disrupt the fact that you're now talking
to version 3 ok at some point you
upgrade to a new version some libraries
where you stop using version 3 and you
switch over to version 5 but it
decouples the the deployment of new code
from the retirement of old code you can
always deploy new code synchronously and
your ways retire old code asynchronously
and it's a it is kind of sometimes
called the immutable server immutable
code pattern because you don't modify
code in production you start a new
server with you know a new instance
effect of the new code alongside the old
code you know the problem with this of
course is that your architecture diagram
looks like something I called the
Deathstar it's a huge number of icons
with lines between them in a big circle
and it's there is no simple architecture
you can draw anymore but it it reflects
the actual flow of the business and you
can pick up in
individual service and which is really
what matters because this figure if you
talk to Eric Evans about domain-driven
design you may have been on a podcast at
one point but there's a there's a
concept of bounded context what you do
what you're doing with micro-services is
you're creating a bounded context that
says these are the consumers of my
service these are the dependencies of my
service I don't need to know about
anything beyond that and I can develop
this service and I can iterate it and
I'm not coupling that to lots of other
things that actually had nothing to do
with me so it becomes much more
productive for developers to only be
able to concentrate on on this bounded
context how do those how does the number
of services and the fact that you have
them on multiple versions and the fact
that they're connected and collaborate
to to provide some cutter and facing
capability how does that affect the
analysis of problems what do you do if
something goes wrong isn't it incredibly
hard to find out what actually happened
because you have those many moving parts
it sounds more complicated and in some
sense as it is it looks more chaotic
from the outside but it's actually
easier to find out what's going wrong
because if a jar file breaks in the
middle of an monolith it's very hard to
figure out what actually broke it
everything is tangled together and you
typically have to get everyone you know
we used to have these emails to everyone
in engineering saying this builds broken
we can't figure out why can everybody
have a look and make sure their stuffs
okay and this is one of the reasons why
we went to micro services you now have a
boundary a failure boundary that says
this service is broken you make it a
call it gives you an error okay that's
obviously broken or it's running out of
memory and blowing itself up because
you've got a some kind of memory leak GC
problem garbage collection problem or it
got a CPU bound runaway CPU bound
problem all of the kinds of problems
that could go wrong are now contained to
a certain service version of a service
class you look across your system and
say yeah this particular service is now
spewing a huge number of errors into its
logs something's wrong with it
right and then who wrote that okay I
know that guy
go call him so
there's a coal tree set up in pager duty
for every micro service and then there
there was a the problem with this though
is that the failures tend to occur one
level up from where they're caused so if
you have a service that's broken the
services that depend on it will tend to
break and what happened was it was an
interesting effect which is that the API
front-end ended up being the on every
single call because everything that
broke happened
you know we appeared at the API and then
you'd have to dig back into this the
dependencies to find out what had really
gone wrong so the API team decided that
they wanted to build a system that would
point a finger at people and tell them
that it had broken this is a become a
fairly popular tool it's called history
and it's a circuit breaker pattern
something that actually were what
actually happened was I gave him a copy
of my condo God's book released it said
read this and they they basically went
and implemented a bunch of patent so
what we needed to do is build bulkheads
and circuit breakers and let's end into
a very useful way to do it so once you
have circuit breakers the API server can
have wrap all of its dependencies and
circuit breakers and if it sees a bunch
of problems it it will flip the circuit
breaker and put up an alert that says no
I'm not broken but this guy is broken so
that's how points the finger that goes
out to page of duty the API team gets to
sleep at night
and whoever wrote the broken dependent
thing gets the call and that just came
out of this vision yourself preservation
mode of putting missus they not being
able to externalise your problems to
operations people it's just because the
developers are on-call they learn to
build robust code they learn to build
systems that point fingers at the right
problems and you get very debug of all
systems and this is part of the sort of
you can think well if I make them make
something somebody else's problem they
don't have to deal with it but it's
actually better to have the problems
come directly back to you so you don't
cause more problems and that's a
different way of thinking from the
typical sort of enterprise developer
turns out you actually end up sleeping
better at night because your code
doesn't break and it actually takes
less time to fix it your than build it
and run it yourself than it does to
explain to the ops guys what you've done
particularly in a continuous delivery
model where you're updating your code
mayor several times a week maybe or
several times a day it's also a lot more
fun right - well it isn't fun to be
woken up at 4:00 a.m. but it's very
unlikely to happen if you're competent
of what you're doing so people that
can't figure out how to build reliable
systems error probably shouldn't be
working for you this is another way of
thinking about it so you've mentioned a
number of things some by name some just
by the concepts like you could use
delivery and DevOps and and of course
the cloud and now micro service how much
do you think those things are related is
it like they're completely orthogonal
and they just go together pretty well or
it is one a prerequisite for the other
how do you how do you V what's your view
on this connection I think in the modern
world where everything is software based
and time to deliver product matters
continuous delivery is really is
becoming a competitive advantage a
disruptive advantage if one company is
doing you know ten deploys a day and
another company is doing you know when
one new version every six months you
know one of those companies is going to
learn and develop and come up with a far
better product much more quickly that's
the transition a lot of enterprises are
struggling with to a more on SAS based
continuous delivery model so once you're
trying to do stuff you know you can get
up to maybe once every two weeks
relative with their monolithic happened
if you're at sea you can do it multiple
times a day but it's it's quite hard to
do if you look about if you're really
trying to get them on lift going fast
you should study very deeply what it's
you've done to do that and it's what
they've done is amazing but what most
people want to do is spread apart spread
the concerns around and I have more set
more bounded distinct bounded context so
that everything can move independently
and once you get the independence
independent teams can have a product
manager they can have all of the
development that works on that piece of
that product and they can have whatever
DevOps person or delivery person they
want in that team and that team can then
deliver
independently and that's a DevOps
organization kind of team of hours and
call them to pizza teams or whatever but
they own everything from you know
figuring out what they should be doing
to delivering it and they don't that
everything else around them is an API
you get a very high trust within that
team and everything outside the team is
an API call it's us relatively untrusted
external sort of fabric that they're
running on and you don't assume that any
API call you make outside your team is
going to succeed if you say to me so
there's no sort of a trust boundary in
this in this bounded context and that is
really the DevOps model and that's the
reorg that most people have to go
through to get to DevOps because you no
longer have tickets and hire handoffs
between silos where you go you talk to
the storage guy you talk to the network
guy you talk to the SIS admin and
there's all these different teams and
operations that you have to walk through
to get something done this is a
cross-cutting key team which has API is
for doing that so that's really why
cloud and DevOps from my point of view
sort of work together I mean there's
DevOps
for just kidding you're optimizing the
interface between development and
operations but what I think is
interesting is taking there's really two
approaches to DevOps you can be an ops
person that is getting better at
automating doing your infrastructure as
code and you start developing right so
think of it as an ops people starting to
develop and building a better interface
to the development processes from the
other direction which is really where
Netflix came from was development people
learning to operate and using a cloud as
the automation layer to provide the
infrastructure to work to automate they
kind of meet in the middle it's in
similar tooling but actually
occasionally slightly different concepts
mm-hm
with with some of the libraries that you
mentioned Eureka and ribbon and carrion
and all of those it's quite obvious that
Netflix invested a lot of time into
making the platform usable for its own
for his own purposes but you also open
sourced a lot of that stuff and what's
the reasoning behind that was there a
pure pure business reason was it to get
collaborators what was the what was the
intention of doing
there's that's a whole series of reasons
and there was some that came up that we
didn't expect I did a whole presentation
on this at one point and there's you
know four or five different things but
the initial thing was that we were
making a transition from depending upon
vendor based code you know we went and
bought aqua logic from whoever made me a
dick let the ecologic message bus which
was got into them or by Oracle or
something and then you get support
issues and you know so but now we don't
want to be dealing with enterprise
software that we pay a lot of money for
and week actually figured out we were
getting better availability and support
than the open source world so we wanted
to switch to an open source based
business model where all of our code we
were using to build Netflix was open
source and we decided we wanted it all
to be apache license so we set up a
relationship with the Apache foundation
we got our lawyers to talk to their
lawyers and what came out of that was an
agreement that any engineer at Netflix
could use anything that was apache
license or that just talking to anybody
if you just download it we understood
what that license meant it also you
could contribute fixes to any Apache
project without having to go to to get
approval from anybody it just you know
it sort of institutionalized the ability
to interact with anything that works in
this sort of under license umbrella and
then when we open sourced our own
projects there's actually some
intellectual property things where any
patents that netflix has around an
open-source project are actually written
into the the project itself as it gets
open-source so you're basically building
a defensive pattern posture around the
fact you've open sourced a piece of
technology so that's the sort of the
groundwork for doing things and then and
that was just because we wanted to be
part of that community and we wanted the
other not only just give back things
that we thought would be helpful but
also get our fixes to be part of the
mainstream because you don't want to
continually have to keep rebasing your
branches you know back into some piece
of software that's moving on you want
you want anything you contribute to be
part of the mainstream product so that
was the initial reasoning
secondary reasoning was we were wanted
to pay our hire better people better
developers and the really good
developers have open source projects in
their names it's some of the really best
developers in the world have gone and
built amazing things and you go I want
to hire that guy they want to be able to
see that Netflix is a nice place for
building software that is open sourced
so they feel comfortable moving to
Netflix because their Netflix is very
supportive of whatever they're building
as their side project the third thing
was the this wasn't not sort of expected
but much stronger short-term effect than
you'd think if you go to a developer and
say could you clean up your code it kind
of always goes the lower bottom of the
list of things to do right if you go to
developer and say would you like to
open-source your code cleaning it up
turns into the evenings and weekends
highest priority is they're gonna have
their name on that code on github that's
gonna be part of their permanent resume
they should yeah they want it to be look
good so some of the biggest code cleanup
documentation isolation taking code
that's a bit tangled into Netflix and
bringing it out to be a separable thing
that's kind of better thought through
cleaned up interfaces you know code
quality all kinds of things it's a
fantastic way to actually improve the
code quality that you use because a lot
of the stuff people have in production
really is a lot messier than they'd like
to admit because it was just put there
to do something right so that that
turned into a short-term business
benefit and then the longer-term benefit
was you can start hiring from people
that know your code and they know your
architecture yeah you can go and look at
you know who are the people that form to
this open source project okay let's go
look at who's most active hey do you
want a job yeah at Netflix maintaining
this code that you seem to be sort of
maintaining anyway right that becomes a
way to find interesting people to
recruit and that's happened quite a few
times as well mm-hm
taken together all the stuff that you've
open-source is something or could be
maybe called something like like a
platform of
on top of Amazon's lower-level
infrastructure offering I don't know
whether you agree with that part of it
is assessment so how do you propose
other companies go about that should
they all be just using Netflix as stuff
or is it a reasonable expectation for a
for a company with not as many
developers to develop their own stuff
what's the how do people choose how to
approach this I think there's probably
three different classes of things in the
Netflix open source get hub account
there's 45 or so projects there now it's
a bit hard to navigate they've kind of
tried to make it a bit easier to find
things that there are things which are
specifically in an AWS based platform
you could look at it as kind of a
scalable cloud foundry
in its it's a disaggregated scalable
platform for doing the same kinds of
things that things like Cloud Foundry do
it's you know you develop it buys into
this platform you deploy it and you can
get very productive developers deploying
code globally very simply so that that's
one class then there's a bunch of
tooling that is really standalone has
nothing to do with that particular
platform like there's a cost monitoring
tool called ice which is very nice
there's security tools that there are
just standalone there's a ruby on rails
app that they just came out with called
Scambler which goes and find people out
on the internet that are talking about
doing bad things to your company and and
notifies the security team to do
takedowns of you know dos attacks or
YouTube videos telling you how to do bad
things like you know steal accounts or
whatever those kinds of things so
there's this is a standalone tool it's
got nothing to do with the platform but
it's a useful thing and there's a lot of
stuff there and then the third one the
things that really nothing to do with
cloud there's some algorithm things
there's libraries for making zookeeper
better that there's this that there's
quite a lot of useful bits and pieces
that have been contributed there's a big
data pieces there's
there's a closure library for talking to
pig I think called pig pen you know
somebody came up with it hey this is
useful enough to stick on gethub well
I'll put it up there okay so maybe let's
let's uh let's switch to another topic
and talk a bit about what you what you
do these days because you're no longer
at Netflix as you mentioned you're now
part of an investment company what is
the what is the stuff that you do I just
spend your days with so to some extent
it feels like what I was doing at
Netflix was the overall architecture
role I spent a lot of time talking about
Netflix publicly and some of that was to
try and get Netflix to be better known
so that we could hire better engineers
some of it was to make sure that the
patterns that Netflix developed didn't
end up in some kind of dead-end
backwater and everyone else went off and
did things a different way it's sort of
future proofing the architecture by
spreading it around and creating a
larger number of people doing things the
same way so those are sort of the
reasons for that I also spend a lot of
time talking when I was a Netflix
talking to venture capital people that
were talking about hey I've got a new
startup with a new idea what do you
think of it and I've sort of taken those
two things which was sort of the pot
sparetime activity is effectively enough
in a architect role and made those into
my day job that's what they do now as I
spend all my time talking to startups
about new ideas and I spend even more
time doing talks at conferences and you
know at this fall I'll be it and they go
to Berlin and go to our who's and
Copenhagen and there's a web summit in
Ireland the key things in Europe more
conferences I forget well the different
conferences I met so what I what are
some of the things that you that you
learn there is art how different are
other companies from from Network
Netflix I think what's happened is
enterprises are trying to figure out how
to build web services that's just a not
it's something they haven't necessarily
had to do before then one of the big
drivers for that is you kind of think of
it as sort of the Internet of Things
starting to happen to companies one of
the companies that's been talking to
Netflix a lot is Nike
who have the backend for their fuel band
which has a lot of customers running
around literally happens they have
London traffic from that so they've been
looking at using Netflix open source to
build their back-end and surprisingly
IBM is one of the biggest users of
Netflix open source they need to develop
a whole bunch of services to make
SoftLayer
after they bought SoftLayer to make
saufley more resilient and have add more
features when they started using Netflix
code for that there's a there's a quite
a few companies that started adopting
either the code itself or the ideas and
the patterns around it if you look at it
then and I'm starting to you know
there's a lot of buzz around docker
right now and I'd listen to Solomon
talking about you know why he did docker
and the way that dr they think about it
and i'm listening to the same kind of
architectural principles that i've been
talking about which is that you fake
code into immutable images which you
then deploy which is the same idea that
docker has and you're deploying these
sort of rapidly deploying that very
dynamic infrastructure so there's an
interesting overlap here than that
there's a whole docker ecosystem that
i'm playing around with and trying to
understand and talking to everybody in
that area so that's been sort of micro
services going mainstream to some extent
or the micro service concept going
mainstream is very well aligned with the
things i was doing at netflix and that's
been a lot of what i'm doing now
only on the other side we have these
portfolio companies that we've that
Battery Ventures is invested in if you
run distributed teams you use a lot of
video conferencing and one of the
companies in that space is called blue
jeans Network they have a multi protocol
video conference that can connect
together all different types of hardware
rather than you being locked into
everyone's on skype or going on a
hangout or everyone's on Polycom or
Cisco or whatever they can glue them all
together into a single obsession a
single conference call and they've
announced a hangout support but I don't
think it's quite shipping yet that's the
next shipment to be able to do a hangout
into a anything else basically you know
I'm working with them they're growing
really
I'm working with them on scaling making
the system more highly available and
speeding up the development processes so
that they can do releases more often
moving to a more micro service
architecture potentially moving from
what my sequel base
you know monolithic database back-end to
a more distributed no sequel probably
here we're looking at Cassandra and
things like that we're still still
investigating what's the right
technology but that's that's a good fun
project for me because it's like going
back to being a cloud architect for
Netflix but it's sort of two-way video
and so that one-way video
speaking of lock-in what is your
recommendation regarding locking to any
particular cloud vendor is this the new
kind of you know database locking that
everybody needs to avoid or what are
some strategies to address that and that
your database is a good example I'm not
sure if anyone ever really said I'm
gonna write this schema in both my
sequel and Postgres or db2 and Oracle
just so I don't get locked into one or
the other but I don't think that ever
really happens somebody picks a 10 you
know a lot of companies might do you
yeah but youth enterprises don't do it
but product companies might have to do
because they initially run on different
databases from the beginning yeah but I
think many products which are really
portable across databases and you end up
they'll end up building to the lowest
common denominator so you tend to pick
the best product you can find the best
fits your need and then you use every
feature at Scott I mean that sort of the
more developer mentality the operations
mentality is I want multiple suppliers
because if I get locked into one they'll
put the price up on me and that's a
opportu mentality and those two meet in
the middle and in a big argument usually
what I see is cloud is is another case
of that the ox' guys want more than one
cloud vendor so that they have some
leverage and I think if you're an
enterprise you're typically you're
already a Microsoft customer and
Microsoft as you as a natural vendor
because there's a lot of windows in your
environment and that you want to put in
the cloud and that's where the best
support for Windows is and you're most
likely with AWS cuz they're the biggest
cloud and the best
for linux-based things and you know you
can do Windows unless you're and you can
do so you can do Windows on AWS and you
can do Linux on SEO so you sort of have
a second source strategy so what I'm
seeing is most enterprises are doing
dual source between AWS and ASEA and
then startups they're typically going to
Google and AWS and saying okay who's
gonna give us the best deal who's gonna
use the you know if your startup you
don't want to spend any money and there
are these starter packs where they'll
give you free machines or discounts or
whatever and there's a lot of leverage
they're both Amazon and Google are very
keen to have startups on their
environment and it makes sense to play
them off against each other and get a
good deal and that's always been that
case you know back in the old days you
know you'd be saying am I going to use
you know Sybase or Oracle and you beat
the vendors price down by you know
prototyping both of them or something so
there's really no no change there you
when you get to it though we're going to
be most productive using a single vendor
because you can use all their features
and you can get a lot done more quickly
and speed of development matters more
than the cost optimization for most
people and then the other thing is that
you aren't locked into a bender that's
putting the prices up and this is this
is something that I think a lot of ups
people haven't got their heads around
really you keep saying well yeah well if
I get locked into a Douglas they'll put
their prices up and it they put they
keep cutting their prices the fact that
Google is out there is causing Amazon to
cut their prices yeah as your everybody
so what you're looking at is
approximately are having in price every
18 months so if you're looking at a
three year cost of us of a system you've
got to assume that it's cloud cost is
gonna be a quarter in three years of
what it is on day one there's a cost
reduction curve so you the penalty of
being locked in is actually much less I
think the key thing really is if you're
trying to roll out something really big
and complicated you need to be in a
large cloud needs to be a small fish in
a big pond
if you're running something really small
then there are a lot more vendors you
can pick from you might if you just want
to or three machines you you probably
just as well go to digitalocean
and pick up a few small machines if you
want to run tens of thousands of
machines you your number of clouds you
could go to is Brindley - just a few
what would you say regarding arguments
that if you're in some of the business
that let's say Amazon or Google do
business in as well you're sort of
working together with your competitor
let's say yes you're a bookseller or a
retailer in general and you have
skeptical about moving to Amazon what
would be your your answer to those
concerns yeah there's a lot of retail
companies in the US that refuse to use
Amazon and they're hobbling themselves
by trying to build their own clouds and
they have these internal teams trying to
build something that's you know doesn't
scale it's got fewer features it's not a
stable and then their product is running
on top of that and they're suffering
from that so you're kind of limiting
yourself Netflix is in is a classic
example of this Amazon Prime is a direct
competitor to Netflix and it's a movie
streaming service and if you turn the
question around it maybe makes more
sense so if if Amazon Prime running on
AWS and Netflix wasn't then Amazon would
happen to try and would have an
advantage over AWS in that it's running
on the best cloud there is right the
largest scale lowest cost whatever most
globally distributed cloud so by Netflix
using AWS it neutralizes that possible
advantage that Prime would have right
and then the other thing is that by
becoming a very strong customer a very
public customer of AWS Netflix actually
gets preferential treatment from AWS and
by being very agile and very advanced in
how it uses cloud you could argue that
it's actually using cloud in in some
ways better than Amazon retailers so you
get to use the features of your
competitor against them think of it as
sort of a judo jujitsu move use the
weight of your opponent against them so
that's
most people don't think about it that
way but I think that's kind of how
Netflix sees it that they're certainly
conscious that they are depending upon a
competitor but so far Amazon Prime is
about one and a half percent of network
traffic in the US and Netflix is about
34 percent so it's about 20 times bigger
than prime so not a huge competitor from
that point of view the biggest
competitor is actually YouTube which is
about a third of the traffic of Netflix
1/3 to 1/2 and Google is a competitor
but Netflix also works very closely with
Google so you end up in this competition
thing where in the modern world with
large conglomerate companies and you
just have to work with your competitors
and try to use whatever leverage you can
against them to for your own advantage
maybe finally as I'm German I have to
ask this what do you what do you say to
to security concerns that people might
have regarding their movement to some
cloud service if they're gonna ask me
about Netflix launching in Germany the
that security is another one of these
things where if you look at the way you
used to do security it doesn't work in
the cloud some people get upset about
that the people that are excited they
were looking at things you can do that
you could never do in the data center
and there's something about having
programmable infrastructure that you can
introspect at the entire state of it
that makes you can make strong
assertions about your system and if you
took a typical data center and say I
want to know every external way into
that data center and you've missed some
you know there's some storage array
that's got a modem that's calling back
to a storage vendor there's you know
there's all kinds of little extra things
going on that you don't really know
about or you can't find or sort of
sneaking around the back or somebody put
up a machine somewhere it's very hard to
correctly manage every possible way in
if you look at a cloud you taken an AWS
account you
okay give me list of all the instances
iterate across them that's the IP
addresses of every instance public IP
and then here's the e Ovie's the load
balancers is the elastic IPS then you're
done basically and you know there's a
few very well understood the things you
can iterate over and you can make strong
assertions about them Netflix as a
security monkey that it open sourced
which actually sits there and looks at
all of these things it looks at the
security groups you've got installed and
tells you you've got things in an
insecure state and it just dynamically
tracks that it's very hard to build
those kinds of things in a cloud it
endless you have a cloud-based
environment that you can't plug a tool
into you have a spanning port of a
switch and gather all the traffic and do
you know detection on it you have to
build things in other ways so there's a
whole new set of vendors and tooling and
actually Battery Ventures has been
investing in some of those companies in
that space it's actually one of the hot
areas for cloud development mmm-hmm okay
so in closing how would you recommend
our listeners go about familiarizing
themselves with all of this if they want
to play around with stuff what's it
what's a good place to start because
this can be overwhelming at times
because there are so many interesting
things to look at what's a good place to
start with I think that one of them one
of the benefits so going back four years
to a Netflix started we had to make
stuff up I mean we were reading white
papers and inventing things and having
arguments and you know trying things out
the situation now is that everything is
much more mature the patterns are much
better understood the tooling is much
more sophisticated and I think probably
the best place to start right now if
you're just starting from scratch is to
just look at docker and build out from
there it solves four of the interesting
things which which Netflix was trying to
solve for on Netflix is just starting to
use docker itself but if it was around
four years ago we've definitely been
using it one of the things it does is it
gives you a very fast deployment you can
stand up a docker container in a few
seconds the second thing gives you is
portability you can build containers on
your laptop and you can deploy them to
multiple different clouds and that
you've isolated the the code and you're
building these immutable
subcode the applications microservices
basically that the third one is that
there's an app store effectively there's
a docker hub you can download something
saying 30,000 different docker
containers that you can just download
and you start it users your starting
point that it is something we've never
really had a portable micro service
store you can just download stuff and go
and play with them and the the last one
is that it's sort of replaces the need
for something like chef or puppet in
that they can the configuration is baked
into the container and that is what is
deployed you're not you're not modifying
configuration at runtime your your what
creating a configuration of build type
and then you're just deploying it so I
think that that embodies a lot of the
architectural principles that the
Netflix came up with you know everyone
sort of discovers these things
independently but the Netflix stuff is
around that so I think I'd look at that
and the other place obviously go to the
Netflix tech tech blog and Netflix open
source github repository and just try
and understand what's are there look at
what Twitter's got look at what
Facebook's got the best software you can
get now is open source and it's from the
large web scale vendors that is the best
software in the world it's the most
advanced software and the enterprise
vendors that you pay lots of money to
have built products that don't scale
that you're evolving too slowly and that
don't solve these big distributed
problems so I think it's a really
interesting time you can go build
something incredibly quickly incredibly
cheaply and that will actually be scale
and be highly available and I think
that's a something you just could have
done five ten years ago it's a fun time
to be up building things okay Adrian
thanks a lot for this conversation it
was a pleasure to have you on our show
we'll have lots of stuff in the show
notes for our listeners and yeah thanks
again for being with us thanks very much
nicer having you we want to know what
you're thinking please go to iTunes and
leave a review of the show this is
stefan silikov for software engineering
radio thanks for listening
[Music]
[Applause]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio net to support us you can
advertise su radio by clicking the Digg
reddit delicious or / bad buttons on the
site or by talking about this on
Facebook Twitter or your own blog if you
have feedback specific to an episode
please use the commenting feature on the
site so other listeners can respond to
your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons 2.5 license
please see the website for details
thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]